Kulom's
law. If two objects have electrical
charges Q1 and Q2 and if they're
separated by a distance R, then Kom's
law says that the electrical or komic
force between these objects is K Q1 Q2 /
R 2. K which you write here as K sub E
for electrical is a constant
approximately equal to 9 * 10 9 Newton
me.
Now, matter can be electrically charged.
Charges can be positive, negative, or
neutral. If an object is neutral, it has
zero electrical charge. Here's the
representation we'll use for a positive
charge, a negative charge, and a neutral
charge. Kulum's law says that like
charges, that is charges with the same
sign, repel each other, while opposite
charges attract. If we put two positive
charges close together, they'll repel
each other since they have the same
sign. The same goes for two negative
charges. If a positive and a negative
charge are near each other, they'll
attract, and neutral charges won't
interact with electrically charged
objects. Now, the closer two charges
are, the stronger the force between them
will be. So, let's return to our
positive and negative charges. When
they're far apart, like we show them
here, the force between them is
relatively weak, as indicated by the
short arrows. As we move the charges
closer together, the forces get
stronger, which we show by the arrows
getting
longer. Kulom's law is also
quantitative. It relates the force
between two objects to their electrical
charges. Here's Kulom's law again. The
force is equal to K * Q1 * Q2 R 2, where
Q1 and Q2 are the charges and R is the
distance between them. One of the keys
to Kulum's law is that the charges are
multiplied together which means their
signs whether positive, negative or
neutral also get multiplied. Let's say
Q1 is positive and let's say Q2 is
positive as well. Multiplying two
positive charges results in a positive
force. And when a force is positive here
it means repulsive pushing the charges
away from each
other. Now let's suppose Q1 is negative
and that Q2 is also negative.
Multiplying two negatives again results
in a positive force. So again Q1 and Q2
will
repel. If one of the charges is positive
while the other is negative then their
product will also be negative which
means the force is
attractive. And finally if at least one
of the charges is neutral meaning it has
zero electrical charge this zero carries
through in the multiplication and the
force between them is zero.
So multiplying the charges is one key to
Kulum's law. The other key is the R squ
in the denominator. Suppose we double
the distance between two charges. How
would the force change? Doubling the
distance means we're changing the R to 2
R. Squaring 2 R gives 4 R 2. And we can
move the four in front of the fraction,
keeping it in the denominator. So now we
have 1/4 of our original force back when
the distance was R. Doubling the
distance results in a quarter of the
force. Similarly, having the distance
would have quadrupled the force. In
other words, Kulum's law is what's known
as an inverse square law, like the law
of gravity. And so, distances are very
important. Finally, just a little
housekeeping, but not critical to
understanding Kulum's law. We've thrown
around this number K 9 * 10 9 Newton me.
Another way to write K is 1 over 4
piepsilon KN where pi is the numerical
constant 3.14159
etc. And epsilon kn is what's known as
the vacuum permitivity also known as the
permitivity of free space and it's
approximately equal to 8.85 85 * 10 -12
km^ 2 per new m squared